A Guide to the Papers of Virginius Dabney, ca. 1976
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Virginius Dabney ca. 1976
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7690-z
This collection consists of 3 boxes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited on 1978 June 14.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Virginius Dabney contain extensive correspondence carried on by Dabney as editor of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, in his personal life, and as a Pulitzer Prize- winning author. Other materials deal with his books such as Below the Potomac, The Dry Messiah, and Liberalism in the South, and much useful material collected as research material for these books is present. There is extensive material on the American Society of Newspaper Editors which Dabney served in various capacities including president. A great deal of useful material on race relations, African Americans, the N.A.A.C.P., etc., is present. Recent political history of Virginia is strongly represented in Dabney's correspondence as editor of Virginia's leading newspaper, and in his personal correspondence with figures such as Senator A. Willis Robinson, Francis Pickens Miller, and Senator Carter Glass.
This addition to the papers of the Virginius Dabney consists of ca. 1,200 items, (15'' linear shelf feet, 3 Hollinger boxes) 1971-1978, chiefly notes and research material for his book: Richmond, The Story of a City, published in 1976. The material is arranged chronologically.
The collection also includes correspondence between Dabney and Alice Fox Pitts, his friend and former executive secretary of the American Society of Newspaper Editors.
Contents List
- Chapters 1-4, (1607-1799) ca. 1976, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Chapter 5, (1800, Gabriel's Insurrection) ca. 1976 (Box 1)
- Chapter 6-9, (1800-1849) ca. 1976, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Chapter 10, (Edgar Allan Poe) ca. 1976 (Box 1)
- Chapter 11-12, (1850-1860) ca. 1976, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Chapter 13, (1861-1864, Richmond & the War) ca. 1976 (Box 1)
- Chapter 13, (1861-1864, Richmond & the War) ca. 1976 (Box 2)
- Chapter 14, (The Fall of Richmond) ca. 1976 (Box 2)
- Chapters 15-19, (1866-1929) ca. 1976, 10 folders (Box 2)
- Chapter 19, (1914-1929) ca. 1976 (Box 3)
- Chapters 20-22, (1930-1975) ca. 1976, 11 folders (Box 3)